hi sorry I got sick had a good sleep for
two days
and thanks to Geshe no time for teaching
uh kilo tears the nephew of my route
tibetan lama can remember take your she
lost son sergeant and he grew up with
rinpoche from the from time he was a
child and so they're kind of similar
like very tough and he has served as the
Geeko observed me monastery which is
part of one of the three largest
monasteries in the world and that's the
vice abbot position and he did a good
job he didn't beat up too many people
that's the debate master sometimes they
carry things and he worked he was the
master of gear longhouse which is one of
the twelve colleges of Sarah may for I
don't know probably thirty years and
maybe a small table bigoted small table
small table I would be good and the he
brought up countless monks he taught
them how to tie their robes which is not
a small thing to teach somebody because
it's very complicated and if you do it
wrong if all stunts and
he I don't know I would say I don't know
500 young monks he trained and amazing
lifetime
he served my teacher ah with this
alright his whole life I'll show you how
how much love he had for my teacher
again I had a green card American green
card and he came to stay with us for I
don't know five six years and then
Rinpoche said they need you back at the
monastery and then he he asked me am I
gonna lose my green card said yeah he
said okay so I think he's the first
person in the world to get back his
green card and he just went home
and he went to train more monks and so
he's been there since then and without
him I cannot do that
geshe course because there's a lot of
rules that we don't know countless we
don't know from foreigner even on the
day of the exam he's tying all these
things I'm Chuck
Kendra he's the tying things on me like
I'm getting married and it's getting
heavier and heavier then he ties this
big bag on my waist and it covers down
to your knees here I said what's that
table
what's the tumbler water bag so why do
you have to wear it during your guessing
exam he says nobody knows but you have
to wear it then like stuff like that I
would never ever understand you know so
without him I wouldn't be here okay so
you should thank him thousand times
he also built many many places for the
monks many what he calls dormitories
yeah difficult jump and his assistant
knowing in 10 is a very good candidate
for gushy soon and we hope he has good
luck and show Sarah J we are better
monks than Sergey ok just kidding
[Music]
and I heard he's gonna teach us some
chanting ok
and I heard he's gonna give a talking
Sedona so he agreed and guess not agreed
to give a talk there sit down and there
that's a totally left on there like
young free radar free okay alright we're
doing class time and I'd like to thank
Tom Brady for teaching class six last
night and it's very nice to have backup
and class 7 is about the second of the
three principal paths which is why yeah
the wish for enlightenment capital W
okay so that class I think it has two or
three classes and they're going to talk
about why do you want to reach body Tina
what's so cool about body Jenna so I'd
like to first talk about Ann arias
experience in pony Jenna okay someone
who has seen emptiness directly and so
the way it happens is that the you know
the five path path the path the
preparation path of seeing habituation
path of no more learning and then in the
first path basically are learning
different versions of the pen or and you
are sorry
usually they say a good disaster in your
life okay like if your mother dies at
your side or something like that so then
you get interested in helping all beings
you get interested in getting out of
this life and then the second path
joylynn path of preparation you learn
basically you learn four kinds of
emptiness to that relate to things and
to that relate to yourself and if you
reach the third one which is where it
starts to relate to yourself where the
pen starts to relate to yourself then we
talked about it you reach
go before and what you reach a cessation
for lower realms you can't be born in
the lower realms so that's a very doable
goal that an ACI teacher should try to
bring their student to and it may be the
best thing that anyone ever did for them
so as a ACA teacher you have a cool
responsibility you have a cool potential
that you could protect someone for the
rest of their lifetimes
if you teach it well if you teach the
pinwheel and I think that itself is a
good reason to the AC art teacher and I
hope you'll all do that you can help
countless people
and they'll all thank you later they
don't thank you when you're doing it 500
times later they'll thank you
then in the last moments of joram joram
cha-cha which is called highest thing in
the world but it's the highest thing in
the normal world you might be making a
tea for your teacher and looking at a
pot on the stove and there are many
conditions you need right you have to be
studying hard you have to have a good
teacher you have to be serving poor
people or people sick people you have to
be meditating in our everyday okay but
if all of those are complete then
suddenly you realize that when you look
at a pot on the stove
you're not seeing upon the stove you are
looking at maybe silver color and a
circle and a black stick and then the
state is opening in your mind and when
the seat opens it it covers the object
and it makes it into a pot and if the
seed was a a lower state like a fire on
an ant scene then the same circle in the
same color it would be a mountain right
hot burning mountain so it depends on
your seeds right and when you reach
Durham Chucho this highest thing in the
world at the path of preparation for the
first time you see a seed opening in
your mind and you have them opening how
many 65 per second but you don't see it
you can't see it so you have to be
meditating a lot and your whole life
since you were born
the things are coming from you 65
pictures our second coming from you but
it's so fast you couldn't see it okay
and at that point you see it for the
first time and it's kind of a fun moment
in your life because you're like yeah
Buddhism's right you know and everything
they taught me is correct and you feel
kind of happy and amazed and it changes
your life forever
you never forget that moment okay then
maybe you go serve the tea to your
teacher and go to the temple and
meditate and then in meditation I would
say within two hours after the seat
opening experience you will see
emptiness directly okay and that's about
twenty minutes although you don't know
how time is passing and you have
communion with the emptiness and it's
higher reality that's all around us but
you never saw it before
and can you think I did it no because
that's not emptiness okay so only you
can see emptiness at that moment you
cannot think to yourself oh I didn't you
know chill out you sharper water point
into water okay and then it's a very
very heavy karma very expensive karma to
stay there
I carry a girlfriend is heavy karma
difficult to keep them but this is much
more okay and it will burn out very fast
okay what's that thing you start
standing on shavings wood shavings from
the abhidharma
yeah it burns hot and it burns fast and
it finishes and then you come down and
then you start to have a bunch of very
cool experiences very very cool
experiences later they were grouped
together into the four Aria Truths we're
not going to call them noble truths
because that's a bad translation Aria
Aria means a higher higher truth so you
will have this bunch of cool experiences
it takes a bone it's called jwe
which means after the direct experience
it takes about maybe an hour maybe a
little bit less and you have all these
amazing experiences like I guess the
first one is you say I did it I said to
mr. acne and that emptiness which you
perceive is also confirmation of the
Buddha okay so that's the core so you
can say after that that I met the Buddha
so we're all Buddhists but we never met
a Buddha the Buddha historical Buddha or
many people are Christian but if you ask
them did Jesus exist we have to say I'm
not sure I think so there's a lot of
books about it and there's a tradition
but to meet Jesus face-to-face or to
meet the Buddha face-to-face then that's
different right and you get this intense
more happy feeling that you confirmed
Buddhism I told you guys my boss in my
diamond company he so I had a deal with
him that I would give all my money to
them monastery like 90% and every six
months I would go to his office and give
him the number and he would give me he
would donate six months salary to Sara
Mae to feed people but give them houses
and I did that for 19 years and so the
first time we did it he said you know
what I'll throw in an extra $10,000 you
know I'm like wow that's so cool I mean
later I learned I made him hundreds of
millions of dollars but still it was
pretty cool and so he you know I was
thank you very much and then Rinpoche
our teacher he would know what day I'm
going to ask for the money he'd say good
luck you know good luck I hope he gives
you more you know and then when I came
home he'd be waiting in the kitchen you
know how much Exeter
10,000 ah great you know and so I
remember during the geisha degree you're
supposed to make a big gift in the
monastery so I was gonna give at the
background I need to bake run which is
at the time with $50,000 maybe maybe
about two hundred thousand now something
and so I I told my about two bosses in
this one you know this is a special one
you know I have to give a lot of money
this time you know and I saw they have
this secret language with their hands
when they're doing deals they they were
touching fingers and they're good but I
saw it you know I'm like the wife's
the boss guy and they had a hand fight
for a while and then he said you know
what we'll give you 50,000 well donate
fifty thousand extra you know then I
said I really appreciate it you know but
can I ask you a question and he said
what I said you know you're from Israel
you are Jewish
everybody hundred percent in Israel are
Jewish my don't need I mean 99 ok 94 and
you're all Jewish there and you're
strong Jewish people you know why you
give money for the Buddhist monastery
why you want to give me extra money then
he looked at me and he said you never
know who's right you know could be any
religion is right so the safest thing is
to give money to each one you know what
am I talking about that yeah you confirm
you're in the right you're on the right
team okay you like ah hey yeah I hit it
you know there is a Buddha and there is
emptiness and so there's a lot of cool
experiences you see your future
Buddhahood about 500 years out and it's
defined by a number of lifetime's it's
called Sippel and Bauer which means
seven lifetimes
later I found it in the Abbey number
later I found it you can check it but
within seven lifetimes you will be a
Buddha and you see your Buddhahood
directly which is very cool and then you
know you will take care of countless
beings on this planet and many planets
and then there's a cool experience
you still have your eyes closed but
you're not seeing emptiness anymore
this is the for ayah truth time and you
see like the face of your mother comes
up in your mind like when you come like
a film on an old film on a real comes up
and you see your mom and you say I love
you mom and I will take care of you then
you see your dad comes up next and you
say Dada I love you I'll take care of
him and your dad's like okay and then
your brothers and then all your friends
and then it starts to speed up like a
what's that gambling machine it's not
machine like that it's spinning like
that and you start to see more and more
people's faces and then you start to see
people you don't know and you say I love
you I will take care of you I love you
all to come here and then it speeds up
even more and you start to see okay I
know you don't believe it but anyway you
heard it birds animals fish one by one
each one in this world you know one by
one
you know and it should take a long time
right I think there's a hundred billion
animals on this earth but because of
emptiness time gets faster so you can
sit with someone for a few seconds and
say I love you and I'll take care of you
and you do all the living creatures on
this planet even amoebas I don't know if
its stomach amoebas I think we should
leave them out but you see all those
creatures and then the weird thing
you start seeing people on other planets
and one by one and you do the same thing
and then it goes to another planet
another planet and you finish
uncountable planets okay each person in
each fish and each animal and then you
come down and it's only ten minutes
later or something you know and you're
like wow and I always tell people I
think after that happens to you how can
you have a bad day you know like you're
throwing up all day but you can't have a
totally bad day you know because it's so
cool to know what your future is and to
know what you have to do okay and that
is the experience of bodhichitta by an
aria okay by someone who just saw
emptiness okay and it's called take
chance I may say taken simce okay
highest Mahayana experience of put each
other and after that your whole life
changes and there's in the reading I
gave you there's nine different cool
things that happen and I thought I will
give you 22 more those come from
Maitreya from the Abbey Samoan car okay
when Duncan damn dance out there don't
make me from the first chapter so uh you
know I don't know how long I can teach
tonight let's see but I'm gonna try to
do those nine which are official on your
homework and 22 with our unofficial on
your homework okay and if we don't
finish the 22 tonight we'll do it
tomorrow okay
alright so now I'm gonna go through the
homework which is not very long say
Tom's Yuki sim
yeah janja means Buddha Buddhahood
Cheung - anybody wanna give me the parts
for $50 I'd make bets with them money
say j.chan
I make concern Tom Mashour a lay up a
chicken and I'm are you coming atcha Tom
be nice today
then they love hearing it Kirra motto
say gee the duration or just scratching
okay okay come on let's chunk Jim wait
not you either
[Laughter]
hi-yah you got another word for Buddha
okay say Chan Chiu Chung needs a clean
away are you're bad these are your
parents because all your obstacles to
Buddhahood chip means understand
everything chip means understand
everything Chung tube means buna okay
chanting is Sam means I just said $50 ya
mind of enlightenment so as you know I
don't like some of the translations that
you see one is enlightened mind the
reason I don't like it is it to me
enlightened mind means you are already
enlightened but that's not what it means
and I don't want to say Buddha mind or
something like it doesn't even mean the
seed for that it doesn't mean done so I
think it's a wrong translation I think
if the person studied well they wouldn't
translate it that way so it's a wish for
enlightenment okay word you can do the
definition um no um it's not in the
darkness
nice simulation the definition by my
chair yes MK money what is petitioner
Chandon chair for the sake of all other
beings yon doubt so pitch on you dude I
wish to reach in total enlightenment
okay it doesn't mean you're enlightened
already and it doesn't mean some kind of
partier which is already Buddha it
doesn't mean that okay so I don't like
to call it enlightened mind I like to go
out wish for enlightenment and I like to
put a capital W because I think it's a
cool I didn't have time to fix the
homework yet I'm sorry okay so that's
your first question those of you who
want to do the Tibetan there's two words
chant to kiss em what is the Sanskrit
yeah bodhichitta so body does mean
enlightenment and cheetah does mean the
mine piroshki gavage chitara chitara
chitara chitara there are many words in
Russian I still have this root to read
or to calculate and it's still cheetah
that comes Russian is much closer to
Sanskrit and then other languages must
mean Russian Czars murder I think okay
there's another word which is common
word for body to the cults m'kay m'kay
this is chick Oh vada cheetah would
butter it means to grow the mind or to
grow the wish to save all beings okay so
there are synonyms you can call it
either one okay
I thought you would like to know some
other divisions of bodhichitta that are
not in the reading and they're not in
the homework okay but if you go to the
monastery and they talk about them
you'll get confused okay so I thought
I'll just cover them for you they're not
on your homework so you don't have to
learn them or write them down ready
how about but um say put on key Simba
table you simply put on key shimbun
table simply Buddha means her sugar cane
and there's two kinds of sugar cane
bodhichitta okay there's two versions of
sugar cane bodhichitta and that's like a
preliminary preliminary bodhichitta okay
before you reach the first path even
okay one is called bodhichitta similar
to the skin of the sugar cane the this
the outside part and then Bernanke king
turbine same k means like the bronchial
table like the sweet taste inside and
you see kids in India you know there's a
people grind up sugar cane on a little
like cart and they have these classes
that they haven't washed for like 20
years then people come and take a drink
and you get diarrhea about five minutes
later but it tastes good so one is
called a sweet like the skin of the
sugar cane and one is called sweet like
the inside of the sugar cane okay and
the first one is when you go to a class
and the teacher teaches you about
bodhichitta
okay so jeonggi shut up you just heard
about it like you're still thinking
about it
okay so in the class you get bodhichitta
but it's not real body tuna it's just
what we call sugar cane about it you
know two kinds okay when you just heard
about it for the first few times we call
it skin okay we call hearing wisdom just
in the class you heard about it and you
start to think about it okay then when
you go home and you think about it and
then you meditate on it that's called
some
tune in come to me Sheriff so you by
thinking about it by yourself at home or
in your car okay and then meditating on
it you get which one
yeah you get the taste the real taste
you still don't have body china but it's
called inside sugarcane for each other
okay so that's an that's a kind of body
children you might see in the scriptures
but you don't know what it is okay
that's a little bit different okay then
there's a then dumb sim case a dum-dum
sim key ultimate buddy Jenna okay
and that's very confusing that means
what the direct perception emptiness
okay it has nothing to do with love or
anything like that lower our hearts can
have it lower areas can have it it
doesn't mean love like that it means the
direct perception emptiness okay so
ultimate bodhichitta means the direct
perception of emptiness yeah then if you
get some if you're a Buddha are you
still a bunny stop by the way when you
get some when you get bodhichitta your
body some real bodies bony but each
other then your body when you have that
experience for example about all the
beings in the universe then your real
body stuff okay
can you still be a body self and be a
Buddha yeah you don't give up your body
self or license when you get to your
Buddha license you get to keep both
cards okay
now you're a bodhisattva who's a Buddha
okay like that and there's a debate and
I'm not sure where I stand on it
Maitreya texts I'll be Simon car says
that to enter the first path on the
Mahayana track you have to have simcha
Chima my ambassador marimba the real one
so they say when you reach the first
part the personal disaster path on
mihaela track you are buddy suffer okay
I'm not sure about it I'm not sure about
it I learned all my Tibetan from Kichler
he talked to me for many years he's so
nice it just talked to you whatever you
say he pretends to understand it
and we had this relationship for many
years or he would correct me and that's
why I can talk
it wasn't camera J because he won't talk
to me so but geisha daughter I always
talk to me and so when I need to know a
word I will ask him what does Chima mean
and then I remember we were driving
somewhere and we stopped that Howard
Johnson and habit to have a Tibetan tea
and they serve him fake what he called
fake cream they call a cream dream or
something like that it's a cream
nightmare actually it's a fake fake milk
it's mostly chalk and water and they'll
give it to you in the cheaper
restaurants if you ask for milk so he
said ah now I'll teach you a new word
about bodhichitta I'm like what he said
this fake milk is Chima this is what
Chmura means this is fake and he says if
you want to know how it relates to
bodhichitta you get me some real milk
right now tell me okay and I hustled her
waitress and she bought some real milk
okay he said this is to MA
mein baath this is non fake no unfit
milk this is real note okay so same gay
Chimamanda means the real thing not like
sugar cane not like sugar cane okay you
get it for real but it's not clear to me
from the lower-middle way school if you
have that experience with countless
beings I don't think so
so bodhisattva Arya then I don't know
what you want to call it the
slot-machine experience ok comes after
the direct procession emptiness okay so
now you have like six kinds of
bodhichitta already okay like the skin
of the sugar cane like the inside of the
sugar cane ultimate buddy china normal
buddy China I aborted China and then you
have what's one more Chimel man but the
real thing when you switch from sugar
cane to the real one okay it's not on
your homework it's just if you want to
teach a deeper class okay alright so the
second question our homework when do you
become a bodhisattva when you reach that
experience that you want to save all
living beings then your body stops so
that state of mind makes you a
bodhisattva okay
Tibet is chunked your Simba okay what
does satphone mean warrior okay sattva
means warrior Simba spelled EPA no
possibly right word not PA means you're
a warrior
okay so it's called a Buddha Buddha
warrior you're not a Buddha yet but
buddy stuff it means a Buddha way okay
question number three on your homework
has everybody stop and seeing emptiness
directly no okay
could be on the first two paths of the
Mahayana track and they didn't see but
it's a bunny children direct the
emptiness directly okay okay but if you
do get bodhichitta chim remember the
real one you entered so glum for
Mahayana even entered the first path in
the Heart Sutra yeah I got a gut it's
the first gut day you entered the first
path you you saw you have that
experience you're a bunny sub okay
first cutting right what's the second
good day yeah party preparation Paragard
a path of seen Paris angered a path of
habituation and then buddy so hot
enlightenment passing normally okay good
so then I have a list of benefits of
getting to bodhichitta that comes from
your reading okay
there's nine benefits in your meaning
you only have to get six of them on the
homework so it's ridiculously easy okay
so here we go okay you can put anyone
that you like but you have to do six
then I'm gonna give you twenty two more
for fun okay cuz it's a short homework
okay we'll do twenty two more from my
trailer okay all right
okay when I'm King by the way this
homework here has a lot of mistakes in
the Tibetan so we gotta fix it something
okay
the homework master this particularly
this last question okay Garen um can't
get you every good thing you ever do
becomes a direct cause for Buddhahood
okay it cannot go to other places okay
you don't get your towels or doughnuts
okay I guess you might get some but
they're all aimed at Buddha and all the
good deeds you do go into the bank to
create your Buddhahood okay once you
have bodhichitta okay because of that
experience you had okay you can't unless
you're having a really bad day like
you're throwing up on doing you can't
have you can't forget what you're trying
to do right you can't you can never
forget so it's everything has the
intention of becoming a Buddha okay so
you can't do a good deed
as a body stuffer without it becoming a
cause for enlightenment directly okay
you have to say directly why I mean
blowing your nose can be an indirect
cause of enlightenment right okay we
have to say direct con all right number
two
Swami cha-cha Rupa are hot whooping
what's the mean word yeah to be worthy
okay of the prostration of every being
on this planet okay if you reached if
you have bodhichitta in your mind if you
want to save all beings if that's your
life's intention and actually every time
anyone meet you they should bow down to
you okay now they don't know who you are
usually so don't get worried if they
don't bow down to you also I'd say
something about Bodhisattvas they don't
advertise that they are buddies toughest
they don't advertise that there is they
don't put a tattoo here that says bow
down to me you know they keep it a
little bit quiet that's a tradition
nobody wrote that down it's just a
tradition when you have that experience
of emptiness and when you have that
experience of seeing all beings and
wanting to help them you don't advertise
it you don't go running to your friends
and say oh I just saw emptiness tick
there's something about it and I think
what it is is when we study anger
tomorrow morning hopefully we'll be
talking about the yule of anger who are
you angry at okay and that determines
what what's the Karma of the anger so if
you're angry at a bodhisattva or you're
angry at an ayah the Karma is
extraordinary you know you could die
from that you
I mean so sorry I think Bodhisattvas in
August they don't advertise much cuz
they don't want people to know who they
are so they make heavier karma said I
mean so it's kind of an unspoken
tradition through ayahs and Bodhisattvas
they don't advertise it because those
people are not gonna believe them anyway
and then they will do some bad thing and
they will have terrible very very
serious results okay from doing small
bad things to the area or the police
office so I think that's why the
tradition of not talking much about it
okay hmm anyway there's no way another
person who can confirm that you are your
body suffer right they can't read your
mind if they can read your mind they
know but you could tell them your body
suffer but they can't confirm it right
so in Buddhism especially in this second
school logic school we don't ask people
to make a jump of faith that they cannot
figure out with their mind it's against
Buddhist policy you see if they don't
have the equipment to confirm that your
body suffering oh yeah then it's a bad
deal to tell them you are and they can't
check they can't confirm you see so
Buddhist logic is very beautiful and if
you fight with your wife it's good to
know Buddhist logic you never use a
statement that the other person doesn't
already extent it's not legal in
Buddhist logic so if you've never been
to the restaurant in Bouie and I say
it's a good restaurant because you know
you've been there then you have to say
no I haven't been there see for that
person it's not a good reason you see so
if you give someone a reason which is
not good for them in Buddhist logic it's
not lodging it's just wrong and it's
your fault
interesting you see there's no truth
outside the truth is what does the other
person already understand and then you
can use logic oh you forgot we went
there a year ago it was good food we
should go again that's that's good logic
okay they can confirm it okay so with
the body software entire a normal person
cannot confirm it okay so it's kind of
not fair to tell them look I'm a buddy
softly you should treat me like a bunny
stuff and never yell at me or you will
go to the lowest hell you know so
obviously that could be abused awesome
okay hmm
st. near on silk in number and here the
homework he has an error okay Sookie
number rinpoche taught me a nice example
I think I told you before we were
watching TV and of course I want I'm not
guess I'm a weren't allowed to watch the
TV we have to sneak into his room and he
was watching a new show and they had the
Queen of England in a row of women and
Rinpoche said can you guess which one is
the Queen and it's like five old ladies
you know but one of them has this and he
said that's a silky number that I've
been trying to teach you in the obvious
among her that she outshines them she
outshines them you don't have to know
which one is the Queen you can tell she
has some kind of miracle glamour in old
Irish sense
she has some she has some glow about her
that's called Sookie number so the next
quality which is the third one is that
once you get body Tina you outshine
those other Buddhist practitioners that
maybe they saw emptiness and maybe they
even reached our heart but they don't
have this wish to help on living beings
okay so you outshine them if they put
you up in the TV next to them you will
you will look more
cool something okay stuck in the mud all
right the next homework answer has two
mistakes in the tibetan in one line okay
get watching saying Cheng you sure it
means every little thing you do becomes
Mahayana everything you do becomes my
Ana you drink some tea
you know you wash dishes you vacuum the
floor in the temple it becomes a Mayan
it becomes Bodhisattvas activity so
everything you do becomes Mahayana okay
you are my Anna you are the Mahina okay
got it
what number was that yeah I'm good even
bad beast now that's a hard question I
would say my on a bad Dean more bad
karma I got out of that one okay next
homework answer is mistaken say
everything you do becomes an activity
buddy stop okay and it's similar to the
last one but these aren't very they're
not clearly very different from each
other okay
everything you do becomes the
Bodhisattvas way of life okay the last
one was everything you do because Maya
but it's the same thing really
okay but it's kind of cool
yeah here it says sternly since the good
deeds you do become the activity but
listen when the last one said good deeds
- okay get one all right that's number
fine
these are coming from pub encourages
commentary okay and you can read it in
the reading number seven okay Sangha
Nagi says who Gong the Tibetan is
misspelled again in the homework e I
like this one this is gal say so
venerable girl says name is Kelsey that
means Galway's say
and it means son or daughter of the
victors son or daughter of the victor
okay
when I wrote this translation 27 years
ago they didn't say he or she they just
said he in English in American English
you know every person who wants to
become a bodhisattva he should do this
and then in the last 27 years they made
it more equal and they say he or she or
you can say they so you're gonna see
that sometimes in the reading and I'm
sorry for I just didn't have time to fix
them all okay okay
it means all the buddhas consider you
you're their son or their daughter okay
and that's kind of cool
Danny's thank you listen case angus is a
target danny tarkanian can return to
midnight some take him it's embedded
Allah no bombing you did our job
this is the short but it's not the value
you can take Bodhisattva vows in one
minute if the Lama knows the verse okay
Danny thank you looks okay now today I
have joined the family the Buddhist
Sangha stated target though now I became
a son or daughter of the Buddha sitting
honey dr. Cheney accountant now no
matter what written can be late someday
I will act to keep my family happy this
faultless lineage I will never embarrass
my parents okay that's the one of the if
you have to take Bodhisattva vows in the
airport with some lama who's changing
planes you can use that one okay our
number used to use it something it means
that I won't mess up I won't make my
parents unhappy I will keep this pretty
self above okay so you become a new
family you join a new family
you're the buddha family and they take
care of you special I know they're
supposed to be equal to everybody but
they're not okay they take care of your
special okay they you will meet them
frequently
ok number 1 7 qian qiu sem Bernanke when
the gong yeah and all the other bodies
toppers in the universe will think of
you as their brother or their sister
okay so the last one was you got new
parents and this one you got new
brothers and sisters okay so all the
body suffers introduce you and they say
oh this is my sister Jenny one this is
my body suffice sister Jenny well okay
so Gail says lucky she got this name
nuns name daughter of the Buddhist
princess of the Buddhist sometimes say
can mean donger sometimes same MO
sometimes it can mean princess but we
know which month she is she's the
princess of the Buddhist okay okay so
that last one was all the body suffers
consider you their brother or their
sister okay
take 10 la soupe say attention na shoot
you enter my honor
okay so becoming a bodhisattva getting
real body children to more money but not
fake one and entering Mahayana are the
same same moment in the same moment you
can now you can say I'm in the Mahayana
I'm in the greater path okay why greater
path because the Yana can also mean what
I like to call it vehicle capacity can
your car carry 12 people or will it
break you see so Mahayana means big
capacity okay big strong enough to carry
lots of people how many people countless
billions in plans what number nine last
one right on this list say say jiggler
Sangay you have the capacity become a
buddha in one lifetime if you practice
Tantra
margiana then because you're a body
stuffer you can reach Buddhahood in one
lifetime okay
Kumar okay that's the whole homework
I don't feel too well but I'd like to go
another half hour okay and I'd like to
read you the 22 from Maitreya which are
very cool okay so I'm making a new rule
on this homework you're gonna get 31 and
you only have to write 6 if you can't
remember 6 you have a problem okay ready
you ain't thinkin you didn't choke every
day on come on come on
Deon sidestep down on me you wanna do
he's gonna give you the
[Music]
De Anza sadawa me dead - engineer to doe
Jerry Michigan down
yoshino-kun amalu capital on Poochie
shown by Commission Donnie Donnie to
vote enum key numbering issue thing is
oh thank you thank you
these are the 22 and I have the Sanskrit
for you just for fun okay
and I think it's good to know a little
bit of Sanskrit it's a good seed in your
mind they say after you become Buddha
you speak Sanskrit okay so let's put
some seats for the Sanskrit okay here we
go I have two versions of this one is
bytes on copper and I figured you rather
have that it's a little bit longer but
maybe we'll finish tomorrow if we have
to okay so the first one they also say
Sun Sun is the foundation of the earth
Shashi right in the sushi / sushi is
Sachi it means that the ground
Bhoomi Bhoomi in Sanskrit okay boo it
can be improve in Sanskrit okay and it
means the ground so if you get to
bodhichitta you get the foundation i was
in what was i I don't remember
Changjo maybe but for two years they're
building a skyscraper next to the hotel
and they're working on the foundation
and it's amazing to watch they have to
dig very very deep and they have to put
the cement very very deep and it took
like two years to finish the foundation
then the rest is easy right but if the
foundation of a high building is not
strong the high building will fall okay
so they spend a lot of time on the
foundation so you can say Foundation
okay
it's a foundation for what you can build
all the other Buddhahood things on it
okay we call 37 Chau Chak so doing 37
qualities or bruna you can build them on
this great foundation you can build a
thirty seven storey building on this
foundation okay so you have the correct
foundation to go higher okay you can
start doing Buddha's skyscrapers okay
but if you don't have for each other you
cannot okay so these are allow you to go
higher and higher okay so the first the
first example of the 22 of my trailer is
boo boo hoo boo and it means the
foundation okay the foundation and you
can build lots of beautiful things on
top of it okay you can really build a
Buddhist body in mind
on top of it okay all right second one
say Hema Hema means gold in Sanskrit
heme okay Silvana is another word but
Hema means gold gold is what we call a
noble metal what's it mean it won't rust
you won't oxidize if you leave it out in
the stream or you leave it out in the
rain for a thousand years it will still
be as bright we're in Japan were you
with me I don't remember oh we got
invited to this private jewelry
collector last month he was in Forbes
you know right you sent it to me mr.
Arakawa in Tokyo he has here's like
2,000 ancient pieces of jewelry you know
he has these crowns of the kings of
Europe they have two thousand diamonds
in them he has a necklace of Queen
Elizabeth the diamonds are this big he
put it on a reed
and we took a picture and he just likes
a diamond color book and he says we are
brothers and he so he spent four hours
of us I mean showed us all these things
and then on me he said come here and he
gave me a crown Roman crown 2,000 years
old and it has laurel leaves special
leaves all gone and very very thin they
feel like if you touch them they go like
this you know and he put it on my head
and I told Scott take a photo quick and
then it started to fall off and I didn't
know what to do and I I grabbed it and
one of the leaves fell off and I like
you know I said how many million dollars
- oh you know and he said don't worry I
can fix it
you know but uh they didn't polish the
gold for 2,000 years because it doesn't
rust Gold doesn't rust okay and
bodhisattvas state of mind after that
first day it will never change it won't
get rusty or dirty or old okay
forty-four years later it's still a
stone it doesn't get less okay it just
gets done okay like gold okay doesn't
ever change the motivation is still
hundred percent to say okay all right
third one
what's a Sanskrit for moon Chandra okay
Chandra means moon incense comes from
that the cen or incandescent comes from
that okay and it means the moon okay the
shining one and what it means is let me
see here Chilton's so doing the carriage
antenna on another bird yeah so
moonlight is supposed to be different
from sunlight in Buddhism and certain
kinds of flowers
like we have one here it's called is
that hmm doctora yeah it's a white
flower and only opens in moonlight you
can see it here it's also called local
win local means crazy and if you eat it
you have a hallucination so some people
eat in on purpose some people die so
don't do it okay but sometimes cattle
will eat it and they'll they will die so
it's a beautiful white flower the flower
doesn't hurt you
I tried to take one from the amount to
my house it wouldn't grow I don't know
why anyway here's some copper Samba
Samba Samba Samba than Germany
Dawid SEPA towered SEPA means rising
moon we recall waxing waxing moon the
waxing moon in in time' mountain ends
tonight it's been growing for 14 days
and it stops getting bigger tonight
tomorrow before moon and then it starts
to shrink okay so this moon means waxing
moon can't wait should Dagny toda conic
on the power given each day then you're
good you're good you're good colonies
just keep getting more and more sweet
more and more big okay and that's like
the moon growing moon okay and that's
the third one so if you have bodhichitta
then i don't know even your physical
qualities even your mental capacity it
grows every day and good days grow every
day if you do more and more cool things
okay like the moon like them waxing moon
okay fourth one is difficult let me get
it right
seit valina javelin ax j JV j v al a NH
mallanna amis a fire a gun a gun Agana
Agana okay that by the way comes from
agni sanskrit so anyway a fire so what's
the fire it burns the wrong ideas about
emptiness okay it helps you burn the
wrong ideas about emptiness and you know
who school is obvious Amon Carter lower
middle way so they say there's kind of
three flavors and emptiness right three
flavors of emptiness I don't think I
gave those to you in the seven but for
example you might say that someone on in
Ann Arbor Dharma track they will
perceive emptiness as nothing is
unchanging nothing is unchanging don't
get upset
if your husband fights with you because
you won't last forever that's a kind of
a lower emptiness okay does it help to
burn your bad deeds yeah you won't
you're back
right or you'll try to stick them it's a
lower emptiness it's not real emptiness
but it will burn your negative emotions
okay second one we can say second school
emptiness yeah so the first one is
called me top atomic by the way dr.
Thorne empty of being unchanging second
one yeah I don't have control okay I
don't have to run one keep tomorrow okay
don't get the one I don't have control
over this husband I can negotiate I can
stalk reasonably I can blackmail no
dinner tonight later on I could
blackmail something more serious
but it might not work okay
what might not work Laura school
definition okay Laura school definition
might work might not work
Laura school emptiness okay and then the
highest emptiness
well this has been coming from my sins
if I want him to be nice to me the only
thing I could do is be nice him to my
kids stop yelling at my kids then I will
make sweet seeds if I speak kindly to my
kids and I will plant seeds and my
husband will speak kindly to me does it
work
sometimes are all the time it works all
the time sometimes it doesn't look like
it's working because it takes time for
sleep to open okay so don't lose faith
in it just because it takes time to open
okay don't plant a watermelon seed and
expect the well me on the next day it
doesn't happen all right so it burns the
three kinds of wrong ideas that things
are unchanging that things are under my
control or that things don't come from
my seat okay got it
that's a fire if you have bodhichitta
it's easier to understand those things
okay much easier because everything you
do is my on a Dharma then you're making
good karma constantly okay if a body's
opposites in the class or a non body
self assists in the class the buddy
suffer will get much more good karma
okay all right
number five is called needy sin maybe
and we'll go another half hour okay I'm
gonna stop half not really don't get
upset maybe means treasure like I don't
know how you say mmm like gold mine you
can say gold mine so needy means
treasure in in that sense if you dig
under the ground you will find this big
bunch of gold okay
and that refers to the Bodhisattvas
capacity to do the first perfection yeah
they're giving they're much more into
giving okay they're much more enjoy
giving and they they're never stingy
they just give give give give okay they
get something and they're given I have a
diamond dealer friend he's a Jane very
very nice man and he donates money every
day to something and I said you know
what don't you ever run out of money he
said no you gotta keep it moving man you
gotta keep it moving and he's not
Buddhist but he's got this understanding
you know keep it moving when you hold on
to money it stops making money you know
and when you give it to other people it
keeps making money so Bodhisattvas are
like that they keep giving and giving
and giving like a gold mine okay you can
keep digging and there's more gold okay
there's a little bit of self-interest
there who wants to explain it yeah for a
buddy Safa giving away things is not so
cool in one way because they clearly
know they're gonna get more so it's
almost selfish you think they keep
giving students hundred dollars to
answer questions okay
in the monastery you don't answer the
question you get a rosary on the head
you in ten can tell you okay but so
buddy stuff is kind of tricking
everybody oh here take my money oh
you're so nice to give me money yeah I'm
so nice
but actually I'm making more money okay
all right
Nitti the giving of a bodhisattva isn't
like an endless goldmine okay
number six out of 22 by the way maybe
I'll try to find it for you tomorrow a
very cool Chinese businessman dr. Wu who
paid for your tongue cop our cafeteria
and you should thank him if you ever
meet him and he paid for the roads that
are not quite finished yet
and he asked me one day to come to his
apartment in Beijing and teach teaching
this 22 and we did I think were you
there shopping or you both no memory and
he had a Tonka of the 22 and I think I
made a copy of it I'll show you okay
it's cool to try to figure out where the
22 in the Tonka I think so okay six is
your second perfection gets cranked up
huh yeah morality ethical way of life in
America when you say morality it seems a
little bit too Christian like very tough
Christians you know if you don't follow
their ideas about morality you're a bad
person so I try to call it ethical life
ethics same meaning but anyway your your
ethical life your morality gets very
very strong Bodhisattvas are more they
follow the Hinayana morality better than
the Hinayana that's a big advertisement
that was made by that written by the
Bodhisattvas
okay like we don't kill better than
those who die on us don't kill and we
don't steal better than those who know
it don't steal
because we understand the appointment we
really understand and we want to become
Buddhist as fast as we can so we don't
hurt people okay got it
that's compared to a rut Nakata
you got it word rut knock honor not
exactly it's one of the five Gianni
Buddha's right what color yellow it
means source of jewels my akhada means
source Ratna means jewels okay so
Ratnakar means you are like a source of
jewels
okay you are like a source of jewels
because you understand that keeping your
morality it's like where you get all the
precious things from that okay and just
normal morality okay also Ramin means
bodhisattva morality and also a tantric
Moroney if you have it okay
number seven relates to the next
perfection No
yeah what's the next perfection giving
ethical life patience not getting angry
okay and it's compared to are not same
or not Arnim means the ocean it's an old
word for the ocean okay Segarra is the
more common word but are not ancient
this is cool because if the same wind
blows on a lake and then blows on an
ocean the lake will get choppy but the
ocean will stay classy
okay so Bodhisattvas are so advanced
they don't get angry easily okay even if
this person wasn't coming from me there
the person I'm trying to say there the
person I'm trying to help
so I can't get angry at them parents
don't really get angry at their children
they pretend to be angry but as I said
it's difficult to find a parent who
divorced their kids they divorce each
other but nobody divorces their kids
very rare okay so uh I know I know in
sanskrit means ocean
so buddy stuff that's mine is like an
ocean and a small wind cannot upset the
body surface man they never get really
angry they get sort of angry okay but
they never get totally angry they can't
cuz these aren't my kids these are the
ones I saw in my vision these are the
ones I promise to keep to take care okay
so they never get totally angry they can
get a little bit angry okay number eight
right let's try to do have okay say
Vadra diamond right Rogers the old word
for diamond I like it because budge
means power and what English word comes
from it vegetable okay so in ancient
times in India vegetables were
considered to have great power more than
meat or things like that so a person
who's a vegetarian is actually stronger
when I became bit I'll tell you the
story okay
maybe guess not doesn't know it so one
day you know I'm the cook for eight
years which is why people helping me all
the time and I have to make Momo
you know Momo is meat you cut me and you
put it inside a dough and you cook it
and then so I have to cook it every day
but I don't like to eat it I want to be
a vegetarian but everybody in the
monster is eating meat at that time not
now and so I one day I told my teacher I
don't feel so good I know I think I have
to go to the doctor
and I drove to the doctor in what's that
place called the Farmingdale it's about
half an hour from the monastery
Mongolian monster and I sat in a car
outside the doctor's office for like 45
minutes then I drove home and I told my
mama you know the doctor told me it's
very serious
and I have to stop eating meat you know
and Tibetans really respect doctors so
my mama was like oh okay you don't have
to eat meat you know you still have to
cook it but you don't have to eat it and
then you know my family my friends they
found out I wasn't any meat and they
they said oh you're gonna get sick you
you'll what you won't have enough
protein stuff like that you will get
sick you'll get weak
you know and that was 34 years ago and
I'm still doing I'm 66 still doing yoga
with all you 30s and 40s okay I think
I'm the strongest one left from my
generation except today but all my
friends who told me don't stop eating
meat they're all dead they all had heart
attacks
they all had cancer I believe that
eating meat creates those seeds I think
the bad karma creates cholesterol and I
think you're more likely to die so I can
honestly say about half of those events
are dead who told me don't stop eating
meat okay what are we talking about Oh
Phaedra okay there's a region why it
means vegetable okay all right so number
eight relates to the perfection of the
next perfection joyful effort so
bodhisattva is much more capable of
practicing fun then someone who's not a
buddy stopper even if they're feeling
sick they can still make jokes and stuff
okay so I you know it's called effort
but really it means fun effort you have
fun doing Buddhism it's fun for you you
know and if someone says you want to see
a movie or you want to go visit the sick
person you say oh man I want the
high-quality entertainment at the
hospital you see so then you have fun
turning things people think you're crazy
a cousin
maybe you're studying all the time or
translator you know don't you want to
have some fun
listen no I am having fun you're not
having fun okay so that's Vadra what it
means is if you often times the word
diamond in Tibetan or in Buddhist
scripture is called me chepa cannot be
split the thing which cannot be split so
it means as long as you have but it's
not for mine
you can't be split from working hard for
other people you will never give up
taking care of other people okay
and so it's called unsplit herbal and
that's the meaning of Vadra okay
number nine will do two more okay we'll
do 11 what do you guess is next yeah I
was hoping you would give it to me
Stanley
yeah meditation okay so the next one is
called H Allah o Allah I means not in
Sanskrit at the beginning of a word
means ah I mean it's not okay and like
Amita ha
amitaba I mean it's not meta means
measure
ha means like Amitabh are not Amitabh
off okay Amitabh ah okay so our
challenge is not challenge Allah means
to move
to move okay the word accelerator comes
from that alacrity comes from that I
think car car comes from that chariot
comes from that it means moving vehicle
okay
so what's an ekala is a mountain never
moves
you can't just move a mountain if you
don't like where it is difficult to move
a mountain
so Bodhisattvas meditation is very very
high much much higher okay if you're if
in the back of your mind you had we're
gonna call it a slot machine experience
it's kind of cool right if you had the
slot machine of experience then your
meditation is completely different okay
it's very very high very deep okay your
focus is 10 times deeper 100 times
thousand times
okay me kappa nothing can move it acaba
cannot be moved
okay alright two more
you already said that getting on yeah
that may need to pay search in mister
word darkman me
tapas Eric apology that may yeah no
self-nature
okay it means nothing has any nature of
its own the fire is not hot by Nature
okay if you have the Karma fire is hot
if you don't have the Karma fires cold
okay your husband doesn't have any
nature of being mean to you it's coming
from you
okay got it there's nothing in nice I
like self-existent doesn't pass the
waiter test what's the way to tell
something
yeah in our translation team in Sedona
when we want to use a word in a
translation somebody goes next door to
the Mexican restaurant and they say it
to them and they said do you understand
what this words means and they're like I
have no idea so if you say you know no
self-nature they're like I don't know I
don't know what you're talking about the
way that will say I don't know you're
talking about if you say is there chili
in the enchiladas they will say oh I
know what you mean it's chilly inside
the enchilada
what's a Buddhist answer no it never was
so in I like to sell it as a better word
for self-existence in heat is not in
fire okay so the tenth metaphor right
the tenth image for bodhichitta is say
Oh shoddy or shut I think there's like
two Sanskrit words that start with oh
this is one of them or shoddy shoddy
means in fact that that total flower
that grows here the Native Americans
used to eat it to for religion for
religious purpose then they will get
some visions with like higher rasca
something like that so the name for that
is a shoddy no shouting in Tibetan it's
called a mensch humble man means herb
okay but here it means like a
psychotropic or something like that okay
oh surely it's in the yoga Sutra one of
the reasons for unusual experiences that
are false okay anyway change Japan near
up to Sherpa here it means medicine okay
herb which gives you man which is
medicine so in the old days
almost all medicines were taken from
plants so this means medicine plant okay
what if you understand the two kinds of
no self-nature
okay what's the two kinds yeah
people and things people and things okay
cool
all right last one then we'll give you
an early evening yay this is all extra
anyway okay to Chiba say Mitra what's
Mitra fen okay
in ginyan then if it's a good friend
Dharma friend
yeah gateways Union which is sort short
name is dishing instance could it's
kalyana Mitra okay okay
so there are some extra perfections that
are not in the sixth and so kapa starts
throwing them in here and it means to
help people in an unexpected way to help
people and we called top Kappa right
upaya skillful means okay I don't know I
heard can replicate this is a story
about getting not her when he was young
he liked to eat a lot of Momo's so
not now okay camera J will tell him to
make a lot of moments and they will eat
a lot of moments and then this is story
I heard okay then Cameron remembers he
gave him a Tibetan broom Tibetan rumours
about this long and when you use it you
have to bend over you understand
he gave him like ten extra Momo's and
then he stays sweep the floor and he's
like when your belly is really full
difficult to bend over okay so that was
a joke
can you ever say used to playing it's
called the Momo in the broom why am I
talking about that that's a top kappa
west up kappa yes skillful means but
what's it mean next time he won't eat so
many he will hide them and eat them
later okay
so that's a teacher can help you
unexpectedly sometimes by hurting you a
little bit okay and that's called tell
people so that's the mitra okay
if the lama really loves you they will
show you tough love tough love and I you
know can remember Jay really he told us
he gave us both bad names I'm not going
to tell you - nice been here
but all day long he calls us bad things
you know and we each have several bad
names and but it means he really loved
us and for me and even a bit inside
teacher the purpose of this course is to
become an AC 9 teacher or Norbert's
becoming a parent just had a baby and
sometimes you have to be tough on the
kids you know sometimes you have to be
tough on the kids like if they're gonna
run across the street you should then
you should hit them so they don't die
you know so that's called tough love and
our law was very good at Tufts mom he
always give us tough love and you know I
don't think he ever told me I did
something right but it keeps me from
getting Brian you know so number 11
Bodhisattva this person who loves all
living beings they be better tough-love
than other people do they are better at
being tough on the student when the
student needs it and if you're not tough
on the student they will do something
bad they will hurt themselves so it's
called tough love okay so when I'm tough
to you it's just tough love okay all
right
those are the first 11 okay and we'll
finish the rest tomorrow tomorrow
evening class 8 oh we didn't finish the
22 did I let me go find the 22 for you
yeah let's finish the 22 let's just do
everything that's getting microsystem we
finished we're going this is like way
back in class animal 7 isn't it was the
cool things about bodhichitta there were
9 in pub unka i told you on the homework
i would ask for 6 then i added 22 more
if you can't get 6 out of 31 then you
have a problem ok so these are very very
famous very very beautiful descriptions
of bodhichitta 22 characteristics of
both each other and they are comparing
bodhichitta to different objects in the
world like the Sun or gold or things
like that so we just finished numbered
lemon who can tell me what it was huh
Mitra yeah I think yeah good I think
it's a good chance to learn 22 Sanskrit
words these are very common words if you
want I can give you the verse in the
Sanskrit and if your yoga teacher is
something these are nice to know and
it's a nice teaching to learn you just
learned those 22 words in Sanskrit and
then you're kind of prepared to teacher
before a yoga class or something you can
share a few of them you know sorry it's
kind of a extra tool in your a CIT
toolbox okay so we finished friend Mitra
which means you know a spiritual friend
Kalyanam eater okay who uses unusual
means to teach people like I don't know
maybe they play rock and roll stuff like
that okay
we had a good time in Taiwan we played
rock and roll again
you got that video yet can we show it no
maybe tonight there's a nice video
Stanley doing Mayday okay I mean the
bass player is the best thing but
they're singers okay okay number 12 of
the 20 to images for bodhichitta say
Chintamani who can tell me yeah
wish-fulfilling jewel so in in the
Middle East they have other D really all
that means lamp and he rubs it and a guy
comes out and says anything you want
there's a really good dirty joke about
that that I learned in high school so if
the boys want to ask me later I won't
tell the girls ask me later I can't do
it on a video the secret it's funny
monkey pretend and M&E it means a
bodhisattva a person who has bodhichitta
they're especially good at prayers ok
prayers so what does it mean prayers it
means their vision for the future ok I
want to be wish giving jewel so this
jewel you find it in the in like in the
washout here you find this module then
there's a whole ritual you have to clean
it with special stuff on water you have
to put it on top of a religious flag you
have to do special prayers to it on a
special day
and then the jewel will give you
anything you want
so these prayers are these intentions of
a bodhisattva are like a wish giving
jewel okay they have ideas in mind of
how they would like to see the world to
be they have a big vision they they want
to be a wishing jewel for people when
people meet me they should get whatever
they want okay I should be the person
who gives people anything they want okay
and that's a wonderful feeling if you're
a buddy stop if you know emptiness for
example if you could teach the pen
correctly then you could protect these
people after they die they don't believe
Buddhism they don't believe karma they
don't believe future life but they are
gonna come to this day when they die by
the way the person who was dying did die
yesterday and in the hospital and you
know I went and taught them to pen a
couple of weeks ago so then you're like
a wishing jewel you have something to
give them right even they didn't expect
it okay even they didn't expect it you
can give them something precious for
their life and that's probably the best
thing you'll ever do in your life okay
you can get people money or love or
attention or classes but if you can
protect them in the moment of their
death if you can be a wishing jewel in
that moment and then that's a valuable
thing okay that's probably the best
thing you ever did just a pen
okay number 13 is called arca archa and
this is an ancient word for son okay
this is an ancient word for son what's
the usual word word I don't remember
Sariah yeah Erica is the old word
and this is called the perfection of
power which is like the Sun and it means
a bodhisattva a person who has
bodhichitta when you really develop this
wish and even as a sugarcane bodhichitta
okay tell me what's a sugarcane but it's
in there yeah you just came to the class
and then teacher taught it to you that's
sugar cane skin then if you go home
think about it in the car think about it
in the airplane pretty deeply before you
feel it before you feel that 100% you
can still help people a lot the power of
that wish changes you and you become
like the Sun so when you're in a room
with other people they are like the
crops and you are like the sunlight so
one Sun shines over this earth and it
causes rice to grow it causes trees to
grow it causes cactuses to grow it burns
bald people's heads right JB and it's
powerful okay so if you have body
chitta and you're just in a room with
somebody you are helping them to grow
because you are like this on your ARCA
you are like the Sun and you are
inspiring them you are pushing them to
grow you can't spend time in a room with
a person whose main job in life is to
help the whole universe and and it
doesn't change you you see
if you stand near the Sun something's
going to change inside you okay
so if you have body china you have this
powerful effect on other people so ARCA
is a top keep partying okay
the perfection of power okay just by
your presence you inspire people you
change them they grow by being around
you okay Kumar number 14 Geeta Geeta
what get some like Bhagavad Gita song of
the blessing one
okay so Geeta means song and this is
called Yashica Parchin the perfection of
understanding and then they say if you
really understand emptiness and you talk
about it to other people it's like the
song of the Gandharvas and anima okay
kendama means do you know yeah heavenly
musician they live in the Buddha
paradises and they play rock and roll
there especially 1970s late sixties they
especially like Neil Young and so these
are divine musicians so if you
understand this thing about the nose and
the face if you can explain it to
somebody that's the sweetest song in the
world that's the sweetest song you can
sing to somebody and people on a deep
level when they're around the
Bodhisattva and the body's office
talking about those seeds it's very
sweet to them it's very sweet to them on
a subconscious level unconscious level
they respond okay so it's always okay to
irritate someone with talking about the
pen okay
on a plane people ask me you know what's
your name on the plane I say did you
hear about the pig so I figure if the
plane blows up and I die in the next 10
minutes it's good ID I'm talking about
the pen ok so sing this song learn this
song it's almost as good as jump learn
to sing this song and people respond to
and even when they don't want to even
when they don't believe you
some part of them says oh this makes
sense you know
this explains the whole world ok so sing
this sweet song don't be shy to sing the
song even if you sing this song lousy
it's better than other songs so even if
you can't sing very good if you sing it
it's better than other songs ok you can
practice in the shower I love singing in
the shower
Veronica he'd sing so ok no she likes it
ok 15 it has 7 it has 7 different parts
ok saying Napa Napa it means king ok
no nor is the ancient word for man and
it became used in capital T the man so
yeah yeah no no forgot the name Naropa
from his teacher that's a long story
if you want to know talked to hustle I
can't talk about it in public but Nero
the
Roman Emperor Nero that comes from nurse
that word comes from there so Nirvana
means King and this refers to what we
call membership a business which means
your power to know the things that are
hidden is like a king and no one can
stop you from anything you want to know
okay that's the meaning of a sanga's
name right talk me nothing can stop your
wisdom okay your understanding cuts to
all things your your insight into things
cannot be stopped
your mind is like the king the king
doesn't have to ask permission to go
anywhere
the king can walk into anybody's bedroom
okay this is the old time King okay King
in India was not like president okay
King can do any terrible thing and
people have to smile and say sure you
know King says I want your breakfast you
know you're about to eat some cornflakes
and Kings like I want that in ancient
India the King owns everything also the
people and the king can't say I like
your daughter she should come to the
palace tomorrow you know and so no one
can refuse the king and if you
understand seeds they can go anywhere
you see I mean understanding of seeds
can walk into the room of any beautiful
or irritating object okay and explain it
okay so it's unstoppable
okay your understanding of seeds is
unstoppable any irritating person you
meet any goal you have to reach this
King can go there no one can stop him
okay cool all right that's 15 I think
right
sixteen is called gunga and it's not the
ganja you heard about okay I think in
modern India ganja means like marijuana
or something I've bent I played a
concert sitar concert at a temple where
everybody was there about 2,000 women in
white clothes in a temple out in the
middle of nowhere
and they were all singing and they're
all doing ganja and the only men allowed
in were the musicians and it was pretty
interesting some anyway this ganja means
a ponzu okay Ponta I don't think you
know this word human dictionary panda
means like it's similar to kosher
similar to coach what's kosher
yeah I chose your house like the house
where you keep all the money all the
gold all the jewels okay and if you have
bodhichitta it is like a storehouse
where you keep your gay Adi munition
it's also a cinnamon Yoshi what's that
mean yeah good deeds and wisdom which
become the physical and the mental parts
of a Buddha okay so a bodhisattva is
like a bank vault where they keep the
karma that makes buddha body and the
karma that makes a buddha mind so you
become like national treasury of russia
they have one in u.s. Fort Knox
I don't know what they still have it I
don't offend matters anymore but because
nobody cares about it but it's where
they keep all the gold in the United
States and you become Fort Knox you
become this super bank
of good seeds okay which will create
Buddha's body and bonus mine so you are
called the bank vault okay ganja okay
old meaning of ganja okay 17 by the way
I'm using some conference commentary
okay and I'm not doing the whole thing
it's longer but we don't have time
number 17 is called Maha Maha Maha Marga
Christine yeah the great path you know
interstate highway highway 10 out here
okay maja Marga okay
interstate highway that means there are
thirty seven qualities that you will
have when you are Buddha and if you have
them you become a highway for other
people other people can drive on you to
go to enlightenment okay so you become
the Buddha highway for the whole world
okay and they drive on you to reach
Buddhahood these thirty seven qualities
someday we can do them slowly but it's
very nice I think it's the best way to
understand what's a Buddha not by the
form or the bodies but by the thirty
seven qualities they have Cheung jokes
will do okay so once you have these
beautiful qualities which Bodhisattvas
are already collecting them Bodhisattvas
are already reaching some of them in a
lower way then as you are reaching these
different qualities of a Buddha you
become a highway you become a way to
help other people and
people can drive on you sometimes if
you're a buddy soft it feels like people
are driving on you but you're happy
drive on me okay you get to Buddhahood
you know I'll be the road okay all right
that's 17 Tibetans have funny corruption
words for modern words that they don't
have in their language so like for radio
they tried the government tried to say
Longtin which is wind wind a letter wind
message for typewriter they tried to do
for computer they charged unum Chuck bar
which means finger pressing iron picture
my friend was on the committee to choose
the words they all completely failed you
know they call Caputo computer and read
Joe and why did I talk about that oh I
didn't know what's the Tibetan word for
asphalt this black road covering that we
put here I was bragging to Geshe how
much money we spent on the asphalt which
was almost a million dollars and we
still need 700,000 he we didn't even ask
yesterday because we didn't want you to
have a heart attack anyway I said what's
the okay what's your new word for
asphalt he said a Locati you got real
alacrity on your own you know so you can
be the early katya for the whole world
okay they can drive on you they can use
you to get enlightened okay that's
number 17 you become a la cote 18 and
it's interesting 18 because it's Jana
Jana vehicle okay now
Jahna can also be well yeah Simba je
tsongkhapa defines it as Simba if if you
spell it with a G word it becomes a
young young person like jump L Shanna is
the young aspect of manjushri but if you
spell it with a bee but you know it
means something you ride like a horse or
a donkey okay that's called Simba
so again number 18 is jana and this is
the jana in mahayana Hinayana okay and
it means people could ride you and so
how is it different from the last one
the last one was you can become a Locati
that people can ride on to get the 37
qualities of a buddha 18 means your only
motivation your whole life is to help
other people so it refers to your love
it refers turn especially specifically
ninja Karuna okay how much love do you
have Karuna comes from in russian
there's a word Krrish which does not yet
Krishna Krishna Krishna
yeah like roof or cover and so Karuna
this russian is much closer to Sanskrit
so the also the word for hood of an
automobile is Krishna and it means cover
meaning you protect people okay so
Karuna compassion is its number 18 okay
and that's the iana okay you are a horse
for the whole world because you just
love them and you wanted to care of them
and that's your only motivation and all
the time okay so Nancy best friend right
for many years in New York is Michael my
who also helped the diamond in New York
for I don't know 40 years and he hasn't
he had a car so not everybody in New
York has a car you don't need a car in
New York a car is a big hassle Nancy has
to get up at 4 o'clock every morning
move her car according to the you know
parking regulations if you don't want to
pay more than your apartment for the
parking the car then you have to move
your car room one day I ran out of gas
moving the car I couldn't find a parking
spot and anyway remember Jay had a
nickname for Michaels car which is
chiba-chiba it means a public horse you
know because he would always give you a
ride he drove around every Lama who ever
visited New York City he was the driver
he's extremely kind he's really buddy
sort by type and he would always give
you a ride it didn't matter what time
didn't matter how far you had to go so
Rinpoche gave him a nickname public
horse chibita this led to the famous
incident where he was looking for a
parking space I was with him in the car
and we found one it's like finding a
gold mine and here's this big empty
parking space you know and he drives by
and I'm like like Oh what-what are you
doing here
he says Caitlin I don't want to use up
the karma I'm like we have to talk about
Karma
anyway number 18 is a chibita you become
Jana you become public horse and it's
cuz your motivation is it's like Michael
you just want to help people and you can
call him anytime neither day and he will
drive you somewhere okay
still I'll give you his phone number
okay Stanley yeah okay nineteen
this was long I'm sorry okay say plus
Ravana Utica press Ravenel Utica and it
means let me get this screen it means we
have a spring up here spring means water
comes naturally under the ground comes
out it's running right now you should go
see it it doesn't run all the time and
it's very beautiful and that's why they
built this fort here because it's one of
the only springs in southern Arizona
where you can get free water and it's so
it's a big deal somehow that what
mountain shape is like a bowl and it
collects all the water underground and
then it comes out here and there was
actually many wars here between people
for the water so it's running right now
it's a very beautiful experience in the
desert to see it so if you like it can
come up to the ranch house and spend
some time by the spring it's a very
beautiful place to sit and meditate it's
very calming okay anyway you'll never
have time and it means you two qualities
me JP soon say me JP soon
if you meditate a lot and you practice a
lot there comes a time in your life
where you remember precisely every
teaching you ever had okay the the video
you can play back the video any video of
teachings you heard and it's kind of
beautiful
you know unexpected memories coming in
your mind of something your teacher said
20-30 years ago and I always think of it
as a synapse firing unexpectedly like
the electricity in the mine goes to just
to do and then you remember you know
somebody is still in asking you what's
me jeppesen and you go to do and our
words from Russian class in Princeton
University in 1970 when sometimes when
I'm in Moscow I I say you know like some
weird word and everybody's like wow and
I'm like yeah I didn't think of this
word for thirty years forty years you
know I can't remember it right now but
sometimes it happens that words just
come in your mind and so if you have so
means mantra Joe and me Japan means
never forget so there comes a time in
your meditation when you can access all
the teachings you ever had so even if
you're gonna sleep through a teaching
it's good to come okay
concern it's still recording and you can
access the recording later on okay don't
forget that skill we talked about the
ability to sit in class with your eyes
open and sleep is very useful now
connected with that media person is top
may chipper chipper Papa which means the
courage to explain the Dharma to other
people
without stopping so our spring dries up
half the year or most of the year but if
you have this power this press Ravana
Boadicea Buddha coming spring right
press lamina it will keep it will keep
coming out okay and the emphasis in the
metaphor is that when you meet a
bodhisattva there's water that came out
but in English we have an idiom it means
that there's a lot more where that came
from
there's a lot more where that came from
so the emphasis on this metaphor of you
are like a spring for other people the
emphasis is there's a lot of teachings
you're giving now to them people can see
your current teaching but there's a lot
more where that came from
because of your Miche a person because
of your mantra sorry your son can also
mean like magic you have this synapse
magic okay so there's a lot more in the
subconscious of a bodhisattva that they
can share with you because they reach
that level in meditation where the water
will keep flowing so this little tiny
spring you see here at Diamond Mountain
which cost the lives of many people this
building we put the roof on what do you
call it nowadays ranch house if you go
there there's a windows like this
there's a window shape like this
that was for shooting people that the
house was built during the worst here
and so the spring you can see is a
little water but it's coming from an
ocean underground
okay the whole mountain range here has a
huge
ocean of water underground and so when
you meet a bodhisattva what they're
teaching is like the spring but it's
also refers to the underground water
there's a ocean behind it okay because
they remember everything they were
taught me before okay all right what
number we on I'm just checking to make
sure you're awake yeah 20 am i right
I'm not a nun doctor so it's Ananda and
octi okay
Ananda okay ot means expression Ananda
means happy okay super happy prefix in
Sanskrit means super long a ah okay yes
they are and Ananda means happy so under
means super happy Ananda means unhappy
so don't call the Buddhist disciple
Ananda he's under okay mr. super happy
it really it's one of my what Maya it's
one of my pet peeves in yoga class when
they say something like a hint sir which
means super violent okay let's see here
this again refers to a sweet song conga
beat da conga we're done okay
it means the sound that everyone likes
to hear this talking about saving the
world talking about getting out of pain
talking about look being honest with
people you know you're gonna die it's
kind of weird to meet somebody you know
you get invited to a class and you walk
in and you say hey you're gonna die then
they're like well but part of them is
happy Ananda part of them is happy
because someone's telling the truth okay
someone's telling the truth and people
aren't stupid
you know after your grandmother dies and
you know your first aunt dies on you
your pet dog dies and then you get the
picture you're usually about six years
old or something you people aren't
stupid so if you walk in and you start
talking about death honestly directly
then it actually sounds like a got
a dark yen you can't call it by the way
the guitar dannion can mean lute or
guitar okay like that violin okay it
musical instrument okay you can think of
number 20 that's like a musical
instrument okay and we have a joke okay
I'm just gonna tell you so you can
remember say Come God didn't do so conga
means Ananda gender means Siddhartha
okay Siddhartha so conga means everybody
loves him or her
and Siddhartha means achieves our goals
can achieve every goal so sometimes in
the monastery a rich person comes to
visit and the monks have secret language
to ask do they have much money for the
monastery
okay I'm sorry it happens and and
they'll say is this person
Ananda Siddhartha and see people go yeah
this is okay let's take good camera and
anandam means everyone likes it
Siddhartha means achieves all goals that
said artist name what does it mean money
so if we start talking about Ananda
Siddhartha you know what we're talking
about okay
of course the way you ask a person for
sponsorship it should be straightforward
and honest but you can still make jokes
about it it's okay okay that's our
lineage right fun lineage okay all right
two more to go
21 the Sanskrit is sorry hang on I gotta
look it up for you Oh Noddy say Noddy
okay naughty means searching like recall
Joe Joe my mine right Noddy it means a
river okay Rimmer okay it means a river
Noddy but it can also mean a channel
where the prana floss okay Noddy okay
and there's a lot lots of rivers in the
world that have the route
not everything the NEPA is one this is
interesting because it means all rivers
go to the same ocean it means all rivers
go to the same ocean and there's a very
beautiful teaching which we should do
some time when we don't have anything
else in there which say tato
take matching tattoo take my cheek in
the end it's all one part in the end
it's all one and that's a big debate in
present a parameter okay
topic number four the huge huge debate
you know and there are tantric vows
heinrich vows against criticizing other
religions okay if you become a high
Buddhist teacher a CI teacher we are
still not allowed to criticize other
religions in the world because they all
flow to the same ocean okay if you
follow that water nadi you will reach
the same place okay
sooner or later you will reach the same
place so you know love other religions
appreciate them study them
I studied Quran for two months in in
Morocco it was very beautiful and you
know learn about them a little bit and
appreciate them and love them in the end
they flow to the same place
so never criticize the kind of shows you
don't know anything if you criticize
other religions okay it's all Nadi it's
all one stream and the body suffer
understand okay and they will use other
religions my best-selling book in the
world is a book
the yoga Sutra okay which I don't
believe in I mean unless it gets
reinterpret but you use other religions
learn other religions master them be
interested in them respect them okay and
you'll you'll be glad that you didn't
okay 22 and then we'll take a break and
we have to prepare for Gila number 22
mega mega which means cloud and cloud in
the sky okay this is a Sanskrit mmm this
is cool
when you become a bodhisattva so in
buddhism in ancient india they believed
that the gods dropped the rain from the
sky you know so if it doesn't rain in
your state you have to you know do a
ceremony and ask them gods in the sky
please please drop some more rain you
know so those gods became known as like
mega so there will come a time as a
bodhisattva when you are sitting in your
buddha paradise and please drop some
rain on us
okay whoever gets there first in this
room okay let's make a deal right now
okay I'm not a Buddha I'm really not I
would like to be but let's make a
agreement okay everybody whoever gets
there first you drop some rain on them
drop some time on the rest of it
everybody agree yeah mahjong okay yeah
so whoever gets there first
drop some rain on the drop some Dharma
okay let me and John know so we can put
our hat on
it's really irritating did so we have a
deal
whoever gets there first you know chop
some rain on us from your Buddha very
cool and that's why the Bodhisattva is
called the cloud okay cool okay all
right
we finished two classes ago yeah we'll
work hard tonight to finish everything
in Tim will be happy okay who's got
sushi in the Sun yes and Big E danke
Schoen
chip I um you know good and I come
me the terrible concern Amish a
tautology tsunami a they told me about
colony topper